Today's דף daf is לד, Lamed Daled, 34, and we pick up
and right after the משנה Mishnah on לג עמוד ב, Lamed Gimmel
Amud Bet, so we are a little behind, but I think today's
דף daf will go pretty quickly.
And the debate in the משנה Mishnah had been that a בכור
Bechor that is in the hands of a כהן Kohen has some
type of a blood clotting and you want to let blood in
order so that it will be able to live, but the letting
of blood might cause a מום. Mum. So we had three opinions:
we had רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says you can't do anything
because he's afraid that even if you let the person even do
it in a place which won't cause a מום, Mum, he'll be
so anxious and involved that he'll actually come to do it in
a place where there is a מום, Mum, so you have to
let it die. But the חכמים Chachamim say you can let him
do it in a place where it won't cause a מום Mum
because they have the opposite concern: if you don't let him do
anything, he's going to say to heck with it and he'll just
make a מום, Mum, but so therefore you have to give him
an allowance to address the case and you tell him to do
it only in a place where it won't make a מום, Mum,
but if it does accidentally make a מום, Mum, you can't שחט
shecht on the basis of that for obvious policy concerns about what
that would lead to if you were to allow that. And רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you can even לכתחילה l'chatchila make a מום,
Mum, and we will see, or more technically, because we'll discuss what
רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon position is in a minute, you can do
it in a place where it will make a מום, Mum, not
exactly clear if it means that it definitely will, but certainly in
a place where it's likely to or maybe even if it definitely
will. Now, and also the point to be made here is that
there is
a biblical prohibition that חז"ל Chazal understand, not explicit in the תורה,
Torah, בכם מום לא יהיה בו, Bakom Mum Lo Yihiyeh Bo, that
they understand that that is a prohibition to make a מום Mum
in קדשים. Kodshim. Presumably that only means a permanent מום, Mum, a
permanent blemish, and therefore the issue in the משנה Mishnah is that
when you let blood, you'll obviously, you might very well make a
מום, Mum, but you can do it in certain places where it
won't be permanent, and the concern is that you might come to
do it in a place where it will be permanent. So let's
take a look now at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan:
בכור שאחזו דם מקיזין לו את הדם במקום שאינו עושה בו מום.
Bechor she-achazo dam, makizin lo et hadam bimkom she-eino oseh bo mum.
So now we're going to quote a ברייתא Baraita that will parallel
the משנה Mishnah but will add another opinion or two. So if
a בכור Bechor has a clotting of blood, so you can let
blood in a place where it won't make a blemish, ואין מקיזין
לו את הדם במקום שעושה בו מום, ve-ein makizin lo et hadam
bimkom she-oseh bo mum, but not in a place where it will
make a blemish, דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. That's רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. So that exactly parallels the חכמים Chachamim of the משנה,
Mishnah, which makes sense, the חכמים Chachamim of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
is רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So that's this first opinion here is
the second one in the משנה, Mishnah, which is that you can
do it in a place where it won't make a blemish. חכמים
אומרים: Chachamim omrim: אף מקום שעושה בו מום ובלבד שלא ישחט על
אותו מום. af makom she-oseh bo mum, u-vilvad she-lo yishchat al oto
mum.
And the sages say, no, you can even do it if it
will make, in a place where it will make a blemish, אף
af means definitely or probably, but you cannot שחט shecht on the
basis of that מום. Mum. רבי שמעון אומר: Rabbi Shimon omer: אף
נשחט על אותו מום. af nishchat al oto mum. רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says
you can even שחט shecht it on the basis of that מום.
Mum. So now what we've done is we've introduced, we have רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon saying the same thing he did in the משנה,
Mishnah, he can make a מום, Mum, but here in the ברייתא
Baraita he says explicitly that you can even שחט shecht on the
basis of that מום, Mum, that מום Mum that you made for
the sake of the blood clotting. So we have introduced a position
between the חכמים, Chachamim, between רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon in this ברייתא, Baraita, which says that you can make
the מום Mum but has their policy concern of not שחט-ing shecht
on the basis of it. Okay, so so far what we've done
is we've pretty much paralleled the משנה, Mishnah, but we have two
opinions now about if you did it in a place where it
definitely would be a מום, Mum, can you שחט shecht on the
basis of it or not. Now רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer,
now רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who was the same רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda of our משנה, Mishnah, אפילו מת אין מקיזין לו את הדם.
afilu met ein makizin lo et hadam. You can't do anything, you
have to let it die, we're afraid you'll come to make a
מום. Mum. So basically it parallels our משנה, Mishnah, it told us
that the חכמים Chachamim was רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, and it told
us the debate about whether if you allowed somebody to do it
in a place where it definitely makes a מום, Mum, would you
go so far as to say that afterwards you can even שחט
shecht it on the basis of that מום. Mum. Now we're going
to take a look, now before even fully unpacking this, we are
going to parallel this, attempt to parallel this to another similar sort
of policy debate if you would by a different case. Let's take
a look. מתני ליה רבי אליעזר לבריה, Masni lei Rabbi Eliezer livrei,
so רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer taught this ברייתא Baraita to his son,
ואמרי ליה רבי חייא לבריה, ve-amri lei Rabbi Chiyya livrei, some say
רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya taught this to his son, and they taught
the following
explanation: כמחלוקת כאן כך מחלוקת בחבית. ke-machloket kan kach machloket be-chavit. The
same way they're debating here in this
ברייתא, Baraita, they also debate in a case of a חבית, chavit,
of a barrel of תרומה, terumah, בחבית של תרומה. be-chavit shel terumah.
What's the case? דתנן: detnan: חבית של תרומה שנולד בה ספק טומאה.
chavit shel terumah shenolad bah safek tumah. So you have a barrel
of תרומה terumah wine that there's a doubt whether it became טמא.
tamei. Now that's the worst of both worlds. If it definitely became
טמא, tamei, you cannot eat or drink whatever תרומה terumah that became
טמא, tamei, but you can get benefit from it in the process
of destroying it. So if it's תרומה terumah oil, you can burn
it, and if it's תרומה terumah wine, you can basically use it
as air fresheners, they would sprinkle wine around as an air freshener,
so that would be benefit not drinking or not eating, benefit that
comes through its destruction. Thank you.
So that's what you could do if it is טהור tahor of
course you could eat it. If it is neither טמא tamei nor
טהור, tahor, you're stuck. You can't sprinkle it because maybe it's טהור
tahor and then that would not be an appropriate use of תרומה.
terumah. To sprinkle it, if it's טהור tahor you're supposed to eat
it or drink it. If it's טמא tameh you certainly cannot drink
it. So now that it is neither טמא tameh nor טהור tahor
you're in the worst, it's the worst of both worlds. What do
you do with this barrel of תרומה terumah that might be טמא?
tameh? So רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, אם היתה במקום התורפה
יניחנה במקום המוצנע. im haita bemakom haturpah yanichena bemakom hamutzna.
If it was in an exposed place, put it in a private
place. אם היתה מגולה יכסנה, im haita megulah yachasena, if it was
uncovered, cover it up. He says, look, even though this isn't going
to help you, because you're still going to be stuck with doubtful
תרומה terumah that's doubtfully טמא, tameh, and if it doesn't, and therefore,
you know, you're still going to not be able to do anything
about it, you have to protect the תרומה. terumah. Okay, it might
not be טמא, tameh, and therefore you have to protect it from
perhaps really becoming טמא. tameh. So put it in a private place,
cover it up and so on. That isn't going to help you
at all. You're still going to be stuck with it as doubtful,
you can't do anything with it. But from the perspective of the
תרומה, terumah, you still have a responsibility to protect it from becoming
טמא tameh if it is perhaps not טמא. tameh. That's what רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says. רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua omer, רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua takes a focus much more about how you can make
the best out of this situation. אם היתה מונחת במקום מוצנע יניחנה
במקום התורפה. im haita munachat bemakom mutzna yanichena bemakom haturpah.
If it was in a private place, put it in a public
place. אם היתה מכוסה יגלהנה, im haita mechusa yegalena, if it's covered,
uncover it. Meaning put it in an exposed place so that it
will most likely become definitely טמא, tameh, not directly through your actions
but indirectly. And then once it's definitely טמא, tameh, you can salvage
the situation a little bit, at least you can use it as
air freshener. So that makes a lot of sense. רבן גמליאל אומר,
Rabban Gamliel omer, לא יחדש בה דבר. lo yachadesh bah davar. רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says
keep your hands off. Don't do anything one way or the other
way. Like, so, you
know, either way perhaps has problems with it. Maybe there's no point
in protecting it if it's not going to help you, but you're
not allowed to try to expose it to anything problematic, to the
possibility of more טומאה. tumah. So therefore leave it alone. Now, it
is not clear, I would say, to us how that connects exactly
to the case of בכור. bechor. I mean, yeah, there's questions about
what do you do in this difficult situation, but how exactly does
it line up? So we will see how the גמרא Gemara tries
to make this debate parallel the debate in the משנה ברייתא, Mishnah
braita, but before everybody objects to the comparisons, let me just tell
you the גמרא Gemara itself is going to raise ten objections, so
we don't have to object, okay? But let's see what the גמרא
Gemara does initially
to try to say it's comparable. So let's take a look. The
גמרא Gemara says like this.
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, on the third wide line of ל"ג עמוד
ב, lamed-gimmel amud bet, רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir in our ברייתא braita who says that you can make a
מום mum where it will not make a blemish—I mean, you can
let the blood where it won't make a blemish. So he tells
you to address this situation but don't actually do something problematic in
the בכור, bechor, don't actually make a blemish. So that's רבי אליעזר.
Rabbi Eliezer. That's like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says protect it,
you know, put it in a private place. Now again, how's that
like רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? In רבי מאיר'ס Rabbi Meir's scenario, you're
helping yourself, you're actually letting the blood. You're just not doing anything
problematic, right? In רבי אליעזר'ס Rabbi Eliezer's situation, you're not helping yourself,
you're just putting the wine away. But perhaps the comparison is is
that both of them are sort of like saying help the object
that's at risk. So in one case the בכור bechor is at
risk, so you help it by letting blood. In the other case
the wine is at risk, let's say, for becoming more טמא, tameh,
so you protect it. Protect the object that's at risk, but don't
do anything that's possibly, you know, הלכתית halachically problematic. Don't make a
מום, mum, don't expose it to more טומאה. tumah. That's the comparison
there. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is כרבי אליעזר. ke-Rabbi Eliezer. ורבנן, Ve-rabbanan,
and the rabbis that go so far to say that you can
even make a מום mum in the בכור, bechor, okay? That's the
רבנן Rabbanan of the ברייתא. braita. That you can even do something
that הלכתית halachically is questionable for the sake of salvaging it. So
that is כרבי יהושע. ke-Rabbi Yehoshua. That's like רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
that says you can expose the barrel of wine to the possibility
of more טומאה tumah in order to salvage the situation. So there
I think the comparison is a little bit clearer. You're allowed to
do something that, you know, you could raise הלכתי halachic questions about,
making a מום mum in a בכור bechor or possibly making a
מום mum in a בכור, bechor, exposing the barrel to more טומאה,
tumah, but you're allowed to do that to salvage the
situation. ורבי יהודה, Ve-Rabbi Yehuda, and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda basically says
hands off, don't touch the בכור, bechor, let it die, that is
כרבן גמליאל. ke-Rabban Gamliel. That's like רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. They both
take a hands-off approach. Okay, now so that's at least a prima
facie comparison. But now the גמרא Gemara is going to raise about
ten objections. ממאי? Mimai? Who says that these are all comparable? דילמא
עד כאן לא קאמר רבי מאיר התם. Dilma ad kan lo ka'amar
Rabbi Meir hatam. When does רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir say that you
go ahead and you let the blood of the בכור bechor in
a place that it doesn't make a blemish? דקעביד בידים. Dekavid beyadayim.
That's where you are actually directly, you know, letting the blood. So
if you're directly letting the blood, I'm not going to let you
make a blemish, I'm going to limit it to a place where
it can't make a blemish. אבל הכא, Aval hacha, but by the
wine, דגרמא, de-garma, that you're just indirectly, you know, doing something, if
you were to expose the wine for טומאה, tumah, you wouldn't be
making it טמא, tameh, you would be indirectly allowing it to become
טמא. tameh. So maybe
כרבי יהושע סבירא ליה, ke-Rabbi Yehoshua sevira leh, maybe he holds like.
And now let's argue the other way. ועד כאן לא קאמר רבי
אליעזר התם אלא שמא יבוא אליהו ויטהרנו V'ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi
Eliezer hatam ella shema yavo Eliyahu veyitaharenu and
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer by the wine, who says protect the wine,
why would he say protect it? Is because he says look, there's
a doubt about what its status is. So maybe its status will
be clarified. Now of course it's phrased as אליהו הנביא Eliyahu Hanavi
will come, but maybe it literally means that, but you know regardless
the point is is that there's something uncertain here. So if there's
something uncertain, I'm not gonna let you do something inappropriate, okay, because
there's facts that we don't know and maybe those facts will be
clarified, so you have to protect the wine. That's what he says
by the wine case. שמא, Shema, but אבל הכא aval hacha by
the בכור, bechor, דאי שבק ליה מיית, de'ei shavik lei mayit, if
you don't do anything right now, the בכור bechor is gonna die
in the next hour. So in that case, it's not like there's
unknown facts. There's an urgency. The facts are known. So in that
type of a case, maybe כרבנן סבירא ליה, keRabbanan sevira lei, maybe
he even let you make a מום mum in order to salvage
the situation. Don't do anything possibly wrong by the wine, we have
to find out the facts, but here you've got an urgent situation,
do something about it. ועד כאן לא קאמרי רבנן הכא דאי שבק
ליה מיית, V'ad kan lo ka'amri Rabbanan hacha de'ei shavik lei mayit,
and the and maybe the Rabbis who say make a מום, mum,
it's the same type of logic. That's only because if you don't
do anything it'll die. אבל התם Aval hatam by the wine, maybe
they would maybe they would say this is basically the same point
in reverse: שמא יבוא אליהו ויטהרנו. shema yavo Eliyahu veyitaharenu.
Since maybe אליהו הנביא Eliyahu Hanavi will come and make it טהור,
tahor, maybe there are facts to be found out. Maybe they won't
allow you to act as drastically. Maybe כרבי אליעזר סבירא ליה. keRabbi
Eliezer sevira lei. Maybe they'll tell you like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
which is protect the wine and because maybe we have to find
out more facts. ועד כאן לא קאמר רבי יהודה הכא דקעביד בידים.
V'ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Yehuda hacha deka'avid beyadayim.
And when does רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda take a hands-off approach by
the בכור? bechor? When you're actually directly make you know letting blood
and that could lead to making a מום. mum. אבל התם Aval
hatam by the wine דגרמא, degrama, you're not directly you know making
it טמא, tamei, you're just indirectly allowing things to happen. Maybe כרבי
יהושע סבירא ליה. keRabbi Yehoshua sevira lei. Maybe he'd go so far
like רבי יהושע Rabbi Joshua to say expose it so it can
directly become טמא. tamei. ועד כאן לא קאמר רבן גמליאל התם שמא
יבוא אליהו ויטהרנו. V'ad kan lo ka'amar Rabban Gamliel hatam shema yavo
Eliyahu veyitaharenu.
Again, maybe his approach is until you find out more facts, hands
off. אבל הכא Aval hacha by the בכור, bechor, דאי שבק ליה
מיית, de'ei shavik lei mayit, if you don't do anything it's gonna
die. כרבנן סבירא ליה. keRabbanan sevira lei.
Maybe he would hold like the Rabbis that go ahead and make
a blemish. So basically the cases are not comparable. I mean prima
facie there are some ways there's some comparable aspects to them, you
know do you take a hands-on approach, a hands-off approach and so
on, but there's a lot of different factors. The factor number one
for the wine to be much more lenient is that whatever you're
doing, you're not doing it directly. You'd like it to become טמא,
tamei, but you're only exposing it and it'll happen indirectly. It's a
reason to allow you to be more active. On the other hand,
there's a factor to tell you to be less involved. You don't
have all the facts, maybe you should be more hands off. By
the בכור, bechor, on the one hand, you're doing it directly so
there's a reason to say more hands off. On the other hand,
there's an urgency. It's going to die and you do have all
the facts. So therefore that might give you license to do more.
So you can't compare the two cases although there are similar types
of considerations, you can't compare them. ועוד V'od and in addition, הכא
בקראי פליגי והכא בקראי פליגי. hacha bikrai peligi vehacha bikrai peligi. And
now we turn to the question about what this debate what these
debates are really about. I mean, it does sound a lot of
it is just policy questions, but now we're going to try to
take it into פסוקים. pesukim. One minute...
In both בכור bechor and תרומה terumah they're debating פסוקים. pesukim. What
are they debating? דאמר רב חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, De'amar
Rav Chiyya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, said רב חייא בר אבא,
Rav Chiyya bar Abba, said רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Now you have
the first thing you have to understand is the assumption the גמרא
Gemara makes here, which it's not going to make necessarily on the
next עמוד, amud, is that a בכור bechor that is about to
die because of a blood clotting is considered a בעל מום. ba'al
mum. Now that's a little bit funny even before it died?
Yeah, even before it dies.
Now that's a little bit funny. What do you mean a בעל
מום? ba'al mum? There's no visible blemish. A מום mum is about
something visible. So תוספות Tosafot sort of deals with it, one of
these big תוספות'ס, Tosafots, and basically sounds like you can say it
in one of two ways. Either the fact that it's going to
die essentially means that we sort of see if you don't do
anything we see it like to some degree like it's already dead
maybe and therefore it's you don't have a בעל מום ba'al mum
once something's dead, well, okay... yeah, alright, anyway.
Or maybe what תוספות Tosafot is sort of more used towards is
an idea that since you have since to keep it alive would
be sort of, you know, the status of being a תם tam
maybe it's easier to understand that it's not a תם tam rather
than to say that actively it's a בעל מום. ba'al mum. Because
a תם tam animal is an animal that you can bring as
a קרבן, korban, right? But this animal in order if you imagine
I can't this be brought as a קרבן, korban, the only way
it's going to be brought as a קרבן korban is if you
let blood but the only way you're going to be let or
else it's going to die. But if you let blood you're going
to make it into you're going to make a מום. mum. So
to some degree you can no maybe it's easier to say not
you see it as a בעל מום ba'al mum but you can't
see it as a תם. tam. Why? Why can't you see it
as a תם? tam? Because it because it won't survive by the
time you get to the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash.
So you see it as basically טריפה? treifa? No, makes it a
בעל מום, ba'al mum, okay?
Because it makes it
or not a תם. tam. It's not in the position to be
brought as a קרבן korban and if you were to keep it
alive long enough... I guess I don't know we can't bring it
as a קרבן. korban. It'll die beforehand. So you can't bring a
dead animal as a קרבן. korban. What are you talking about? I
mean meaning
it'll die
before we actually get there? Yes. Yes. Okay. All
right.
So that's clearly the assumption of the גמרא. Gemara. תוספות Tosafot sort
of grapples with exactly why, but it sees the fact that it
has a blood clot as if it were a בעל מום ba'al
mum and therefore it's going to frame the part of the issue
here of whether you can make a מום mum in an animal
that already has a מום. mum. That's the way it's going to
be framed, but it never spells out why we consider this to
be as if it already has a מום. mum. So let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Let's just look at it. It
would have to happen
in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash then. I suppose. Right. Yes. This
lacks of רחמנות, Rachmanut, common sense, right?
And halachic category.
You mean about like just letting this animal not suffer and die?
Type of common sense?
This, I mean, the idea if it's not a טריפה, treifa, it
doesn't have a מום, mum, right? But you know it's not going
to survive. So it's you're trying to shoehorn, you're trying to find
some halachic category so that common sense can prevail.
Well, that might be. And it could be when the גמרא Gemara
calls it making a מום mum in a בעל מום, ba'al mum,
it's more like of an analogy than literally calling it a בעל
מום. ba'al mum. So let's take a look at what let's take
all right. Let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara says.
So the גמרא Gemara says, so, הכל מודים במחמיץ אחר מחמיץ שהוא
חייב. hakol modim b'mechameitz achar mechameitz shehu chayav.
Everybody remember this from way back in מנחות? Menachos? How long ago
was that? Like six months? Anyway, or maybe. So you're not allowed,
you know, you're not allowed
to make a מנחה mincha into חמץ. chameitz. Okay?
So what does it mean to make it into חמץ? chameitz? So
it means let's say, you know, as you're kneading the dough, לא
תאפה חמץ. lo teiafeh chameitz.
And one פסוק pasuk says לא תאפה חמץ, lo teiafeh chameitz, the
other says לא תעשה חמץ. lo teiaseh chameitz. You should not bake
it, you should not make it. And from the fact that it
says it in two ways, it means that even if you do
something making it חמץ chameitz after it's already become חמץ. chameitz. So
what does it mean? I'm kneading the dough and I'm, you know,
leaving it around and in the process before I even bake it,
I just leave it around and it ferments. So I now have
made this מנחה mincha into חמץ. chameitz. Now Michael comes and he
bakes it as a מנחה. mincha. So he's, you know, he's baking
dough and making bread that is חמץ. chameitz.
So that is so he doesn't know it's חמץ? chameitz?
You're saying he does? Let's say he does. Let's say he does.
We're both חייב. chayav. Now because the idea there is that we've
made something that is fermented. We haven't just allowed it to ferment.
If that's all you say, then once I've allowed it to ferment,
he can't allow it to ferment again. It's already over and done
with. It's already become fermented. So the fact is that we've created
something that is חמץ. chameitz. So I've created it partly and he's
created it partly and we're both חייב. chayav. So הכל מודים במחמיץ
אחר מחמיץ שהוא חייב, hakol modim b'mechameitz achar mechameitz shehu chayav, דכתיב
d'chsiv לא תאפה חמץ lo teiafeh chameitz ולא תעשה. v'lo teiaseh. One
says don't bake it and the other says don't make it to
tell you that whatever stage you do that is part of the
making of this as חמץ, chameitz, as a חמץ chameitz thing, that
you transgress even though it is already חמץ chameitz and even though
the state is already there. במסרס אחר מסרס שהוא חייב. b'mesareis achar
mesareis shehu chayav. How about the Torah says, right, it says that
you are not allowed, ובארצכם לא תעשו. u'v'artzechem lo sa'asu. It speaks
about מרוח וכתות ונתוק וכרות, m'ruach v'chasuach v'nasuk v'charus, you know, לא
תקריבו אלה להשם lo takrivu eileh l'Hashem ובארצכם לא
תעשו. u'v'artzechem lo sa'asu. That you are not allowed to actually
sterilize or cut off the genitals of animals, which actually creates a
whole problem for veterinarians because that's actually a very major source of
their job and פרנסה. parnassah. So anyway, serious,
it's a real question. Anyway, okay, so what if you basically one
person did one act to the genitals? It's not exactly clear exactly
what we're talking about here. רש"י Rashi tells us to figure it
out. And the other basically finished, completed it. So even though after
the first act the animal was still already sterile, the other person
came and he completed let's say the severing of the genitals so
that he wasn't more sterilizing it, but it was certainly more cutting
away the genitals. And everybody would agree that you're חייב chayav there
as well. Even though in both of these cases, the point is
in both of these cases you might think, you know, the significance
of the act was already completed at the first stage. It was
already חמץ. chameitz. The animal was already sterile. Nevertheless, if you do
yet another act in that process, you transgress as well. דכתיב d'chsiv
ומרוח וכתות ונתוק וכרות. u'v'uach v'chasuach v'nasuk v'charus. So crushed and severed
and, you know, cut off, different types of stages of destroying or
severing the genitals. אם על הכורת חייב על הנתוק לא כל שכן?
im al hakoris chayav, al hanoseik lo kol shekein? If you're חייב
chayav for an initial type of a cutting, you should certainly be
חייב chayav for a complete removal. אלא להביא נתוק אחר כורת. ella
l'havi noseik achar koris. That even the person that completely removes it
after one person has severed, that person is חייב chayav as well.
Okay, so everybody agrees שהוא חייב. shehu chayav. That in both of
those cases, even after it's already been done, you do another stage
of the process, you transgress. לא נחלקו אלא במטיל מום בבעל מום.
lo necheleku ella b'matil mum b'ba'al mum. The only debate is making
a blemish in an animal that's already blemished. Right? So it already
can't be brought as a קרבן, korban, so you have not taken
it further away from the altar, but maybe the fact that it
is a קרבן, korban, the idea of, you know, blemishing it is
intrinsically problematic even if... It is already not able to be brought.
דרבי מאיר סבר, DeRabbi Meir savar, Rabbi Meir holds כל מום לא
יהיה בו. Kol mum lo yiheye bo. That's the verse that we
learned from that you cannot make a blemish. No blemish shall be
in it, which we read you shall not make in it. So
כל מום, kol mum, no blemish, regardless, can't make a blemish in
a קרבן korban regardless if it already is blemished. For רבנן Rabbanan
and the רבנן Rabbanan סבירא סבר svira savar hold תמימי יהיה לרצון.
Temimi yiheye leratzon. The end of the verse is, I mean the
beginning of the verse I think, תמימי יהיה לרצון כל מום לא
יהיה בו, Temimi yiheye leratzon kol mum lo yiheye bo, is that
only if the alternative to a מום mum is תמים. tamim. If
by making the blemish you stopped it from being a תמים, tamim,
then you can't make a blemish. But if it's already not a
תמים, tamim, not an unblemished that's not perfect in that way physically,
then there is no problem of you going ahead now and making
a blemish. So that's how we understand the debate. That רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir said that why does רבי שמעון והחכמים Rabbi Shimon vehachachamim
let you make a blemish in this animal that is has a
blood clot? We would have thought it's because your interest is not
to make the blemish, your interest is just to save the animal
and because somehow your intent is otherwise, but the גמרא Gemara here
is saying no, that's not what it's about. In a minute it'll
say that's what it's about, but not now. Now it's saying that
the reason it's allowed is because since it has a blood clot
it's like it already has a blemish and therefore you're allowed to
go ahead and make a blemish, another blemish. Now, I want to
now say that you know notice again the גמרא Gemara never spelled
out as I said before that a blood clot is like a
blemish. And it's possible to say that we're really making more of
an analogy. Why is it allowed to make a blemish in an
animal that already has a blemish? Because it's not going to be
תמים לרצון. tamim leratzon. It's not going to be able to be
brought as a קרבן korban anyway, so your making a blemish didn't
do anything wrong. So if an animal had a blood clot and
it's about to die, I don't know if you have to say
it's like it has a blemish, all maybe it's enough just to
say it's not going to be תמים לרצון. tamim leratzon. It's not
going to be able to be brought as a קרבן. korban. So
since it's not going to be able to be brought as a
קרבן, korban, you don't do anything wrong by making a blemish. So
maybe I in my mind it's a little easier to say it's
an analogy to that case. It's not exactly calling it a blemish.
Okay, but either way the גמרא Gemara understands that if you're allowed
to make a מום mum in an animal with a מום, mum,
that is רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon position, that you're allowed to make
it in this animal with this blood clot. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues. That's what the debate there is.
Now the גמרא Gemara says like this, so the גמרא Gemara says
ורבי מאיר האי תמימי יהיה לרצון מאי עביד ליה? VeRabbi Meir hai
temimi yiheye leratzon mai avid leih? What does רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
do with the verse about it being unblemished, which sounds like only
when it's unblemished is there a prohibition? מיבעי ליה למעוטי בעל מום
מעיקרא. Miba'ei leih lema'utei ba'al mum mei'ikara. No, he says yes, there
are some animals that you cannot make a blemish in if it
was if that you can make if it had a blemish from
the moment it was born. That's that was never started its life
as תמים. tamim. But if it started its life as תמים, tamim,
now you cannot make one even if it has already a blemish.
So the גמרא Gemara says one minute. בעל מום מעיקרא פשיטא. Ba'al
mum mei'ikara peshita. Of course you can make a blemish in an
animal that was started off with a blemish from the moment it
was born. Why or from before I should say מעיקרא mei'ikara is
not the moment it's born, before you sanctified it. דקלא
בעלמא הוא.
Dikla
be'alma
hu. It's just like a palm tree. Meaning it has it's not
a status of a קרבן korban at all. Now, the question is
what are you talking about? If it's a בכור bechor that is
born with a blemish you might remember going back to that פרק
perek that a בכור bechor born with a blemish has the קדושת
בכור kedushat bechor because you don't have to sanctify it. So that
actually should be the exact same debate. So the גמרא Gemara is
no longer talking about בכור. bechor. The prohibition of making a blemish
in an animal in an animal applies to a קרבן korban applies
to all קרבנות korbanot and the verse is not limited to בכור.
bechor. So we're not in בכור bechor world here, we're in a
normal קרבן korban place. A normal קרבן korban place, if you sanctify
an animal with a blemish, it's like you sanctified your car, like
you sanctified like the גמרא Gemara says a palm tree. It has
no קדושת קרבן. kedushat korban. So the whole concept of blemish is
irrelevant. It's a different type of a קדושה. kedusha. So the גמרא
Gemara says we don't need a פסוק pasuk to allow a case
of making a blemish in an animal that was sanctified with a
blemish. That doesn't that's not even a קרבן korban to begin with.
Then you
would redeem it, but the way but it's like having sanctified your
car, it's not like having sanctified a קרבן, korban, which you redeem
and then you use and the money goes to the בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash. Not at all... right, it has קדושה, kedusha, but not
a קדושה kedusha that's related to the world of קרבנות, korbanot, at
least not directly. Yes.
But you can take you can put the wood of the palm
tree on the altar.
Okay, so maybe so maybe that example... look, it's I'm not getting
into that. You're right, there are two concepts which are not the
same. One is קדושת דמים kedushat damim versus קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf
and the other is קדושת מזבח kedushat mizbe'ach versus קדושת בדק הבית.
kedushat bedek habayit. Anyway, we're not going there right now. Anyway, the
גמרא Gemara says like this: אלא
למעוטי פסולי המוקדשים לאחר פדיונם. Ela lema'utei pesulei hamukdashim le'achar pidyonam. Okay,
you're right. But that you don't need a פסוק pasuk for. But
what you need the פסוק pasuk for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir for
תמים tamim is not to tell you it's generally allowed if it
has a blemish, but to tell you in one case it is
allowed if it already has a blemish, which is what? It had
a blemish and you redeemed it. It no longer is a has
קדושת קרבן kedushat korban now. That you might say is also patently
obvious, it's been redeemed. But no, if you remember yesterday we talked
about things after they've been redeemed, a בכור bechor with a blemish
that still has some of its original status left. So maybe... even
now it'd be forbidden. So סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka daitach amina, I
might have thought הואיל ואסיר בגיזה ועבודה ho'il ve'asir begiza ve'avoda since
it still has some prohibitions even after it's been redeemed. You can't
shear it or work it. במומי נמי לצרמי bemumi nami litsremi maybe
you also can't make a blemish, maybe to some degree it's still
like a קרבן. korban. קא משמע לן. ka mashma lan. So it
tells you no, that that that not only had a blemish but
has been redeemed, that you're allowed to. But while it still has
the sanctity of a קרבן, korban, you cannot make a מום mum
even with a מום. mum. That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says.
ורבנן נמי הכתיב כל מום לא יהיה בו. verabanan nami haktiv kol
mum lo yiheyeh bo. Okay, so now what do the rabbis do
with the verse that says any blemish? They say you're allowed to
if it's already has a blemish. So what do they do with
the any, which seems to broaden the scope of what's prohibited? לגרמא
הוא דאתי legrama hu de'ati to prohibit even doing it indirectly. דתניא
detanya we taught in a ברייתא, braita, מום לא יהיה בו, mum
lo yiheyeh bo, it cannot have a blemish. אין לי אלא
שלא יתן בו מום. ein li ela shelo yiten bo mum. I
only know that you can't actually directly make a blemish. מניין שלא
יביא דבילה ובצק ויניחנה על האוזן? minayin shelo yavi dveila uvatsek veyanichena
al ha'ozen? How do I know that you cannot bring like some
type of a dough or like a, you know, like a some
type of a sticky
fruit
and stick it to your קרבן's korban ear? Okay, so there you
have it. You bring it in a place where there are like
a lot of dogs and you take some nice little dough and
you wrap it around the ear of your קרבן. korban. So how
do you right, so make it like a little קרעפלאך kreplach for
the dogs. כדי שיבא כלב ויאכלנו kedei sheyavo kelev veyochlenu
so the dog goes and takes a bite out of the dough
and takes a bite off of the animal's ear. How do you
know you can't indirectly cause it to have a מום? mum? תלמוד
לומר talmud lomar the verse says כל מום, kol mum, any blemish.
אחד מום ואחד כל מום, echad mum ve'echad kol mum, whether you
directly make it or anything even as you indirectly. So therefore, that's
not allowed, but it is allowed if it already has a blemish.
Now I might point out that it's interesting the גמרא Gemara never
asks how do we know according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that
that's forbidden. Maybe it's not. But the other point being that there's
a bit of a חידוש chiddush here because, you know, this idea
about doing something after the end result is already there is like,
you know, from a בריסקר Brisker perspective, like these, you know, like
this approach of like, you know, sort of trying to define these
issues in sort of in
conceptual terms or well-defined conceptual terms, you know, the classic question to
ask by these types of questions is, is the problem the act
or is the problem what, you know, what the, what it produces,
the end result? So it would seem that that's exactly the debate.
If it already has a blemish, then the רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says it's in that case that it's forbidden. He would say that
the problem is the act of making the blemish. וחכמים vechachamim who
say it's permissible say that it's no, it's the end result of
causing it to be blemished. Okay, and therefore since it's the end
result of causing it to be blemished, it's permissible if it already
has a blemish. So then you also understand why that is linked
to the idea of גרמא grama is also prohibited, right? Because if
it's about causing the, bringing about the end result, then whether I
do it directly or indirectly, I've brought about the end result. That's
the גרמא. grama. But that's limited to a case when it's unblemished.
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who says you're חייב chayav even if it's
blemished, for him it's not about changing the end result, it's about
doing the act. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir might actually say that
גרמא grama is not prohibited. You see these are flip sides of
the coin, right? The חכמים chachamim who say it's only when it's
unblemished, it's creating the result, they say oh but also if you
do it indirectly. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who says the problem is
making the blemish even if it already has a blemish, so maybe
it's not about indirect, maybe it's about the act of making the
blemish, not about causing it to become blemished. Okay, so that is
anyway, that is what the debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and
the חכמים chachamim are, and that's at least how we're explaining why
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon allows you to directly make a blemish because
of the fact that it is has blood clotting is like it
already has one. Now we go on. So that's the debate based
on פסוקים pesukim by the בכור. bechor. ובהא בקרא פליגי uvha bikra
pligi
and here by the תרומה, terumah, what do you do with the
תרומה terumah that is doubtfully טמא? tamei? It's also a question of
פסוקים. pesukim. What's the question? דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל וכן אמר
ריש לקיש וכן אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה, de'amar Rav
Yehuda amar Shmuel vechen amar Reish Lakish vechen amar Rav Nachman amar
Rabbah bar Avuha, so a whole different range of אמוראים Amoraim said,
here's what it's based on. ואני הנה נתתי לך את משמרת תרומותי,
va'ani hinei natati lecha et mishmeret trumotai, I have given you the
guarding of my תרומות. trumot. So in the plural. רבי אליעזר סבר,
Rabbi Eliezer savar, בשתי תרומות הכתוב מדבר, bishtei trumot hakatuv medaber, it's
talking about two תרומות trumot that you have to have a משמרת,
mishmeret, a guarding of. Now obviously you don't have to guard תרומה
טמאה, terumah tmeiah, it's already טמא, tamei, you don't have to protect
it. So what are the two תרומות trumot you have to protect?
How are these two written? Because it says תרומותי trumotai
spelled תרומתי, trumati, we're going to get to that. But they're spelled
the same way actually, but anyway. What? תרומות trumot is spelled
that's written תרומתי.
trumati.
Oh I see, without a ו. vav. Right. So אחת תרומה טהורה
ואחת תרומה תלויה, achat terumah tehorah ve'achat terumah tluyah, whether it is
definitely טהור tahor or whether it is doubtful, both תרומות trumot you
have a responsibility to protect. So that's why he's saying if it's
doubtful, put it in a protected place. You still have to protect
it even if it's not going to help you, you have to
protect its status, it might be טהור. tahor. ואמר רחמנא עביד ליה
שימור, ve'amar Rachmana avid lei shimur, protect it, do something to protect
it. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua and רבי Rabbi He should say back,
תרומתי כתיב, terumati ketiv, as Michael said, it is written without the
ו. vav. So you could, based on the way it is written,
you would read it תרומתי, terumati, my singular. You have no obligation
to protect it. If you have no obligation to protect it, if
you have no obligation to protect it, and so what are you
going to do to improve your situation? Allow it to become טמא,
tamei, expose it, put it in a public place, and if it
is טמא, tamei, then you can at least use it as air
freshener. So therefore, that is what they are debating and it has
nothing to do with, it is all comparable, not only is it
not in terms of the details comparable to the בכור bechor case,
it is based on different פסוקים pesukim and different considerations. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says, למימרא דרבי אליעזר סבר יש אם למקרא.
lememra deRabbi Eliezer savar yeish em lamikra. This sounds like, so you
are saying that Rabbi Eliezer says you go by how the פסוק
pasuk is read, not how it is written, right? תרומותי, terumotai, it
is read תרומותי terumotai in the plural, which means protect even the
תרומה תלויה, terumah teluyah, but it is written, as Michael points out,
without the ו, vav, תרומתי terumati is how, based on just graphically,
how it is written.
And therefore that was, so that is the question of do you
go by the way it is read, יש אם למקרא, yeish em
lamikra, or by the way it is, I am sorry, by the
way it is right, read, יש אם למקרא, yeish em lamikra, the
way it is written, יש אם למסורת. yeish em lamesoret. So now
we are saying that it sounds like you are saying Rabbi Eliezer
holds יש אם למקרא, yeish em lamikra, but is that really true?
ורמינהי, Ureminhei, I will ask you about this. בבגדו בה, Bevigdo vah,
it says that, you know, father sells his daughter as a slave
and then it says that, you know, he can no longer sell
her בבגדו בה. bevigdo vah. What is the פסוק? pasuk? לעם נכרי
לא ימשל למכרה בבגדו בה.
Le’am nochri lo
yimshol lemochrah bevigdo vah.
Okay, so if the, so he can no longer sell her
to somebody else after בבגדו
בה. bevigdo vah.
Now what does בבגדו בה bevigdo vah mean? So, כיון שפירש טליתו
עליה שוב אינו רשאי למכרה. keivan shepeirash talito aleiha shuv eino rashai
lemochrah. So the first way it is reading is בגד, beged, a
garment. Once he spreads his cloak over her, the first master, meaning
he chooses to marry her, because after being sold as a slave
the person who bought her can turn her into his wife. So
if he chooses to marry her, and then let us say the
guy dies or divorces her, the father cannot sell her again. דברי
רבי עקיבא. Divrei Rabbi Akiva. That is what Rabbi Akiva says, that
בגד beged reads as cloak. Which the גמרא Gemara פריך parich says,
אין שפחה אחר אישות, ein shifchah achar ishut, that you cannot have,
you cannot sell her as a slave after she has been married,
or אחר אישה, achar isha, excuse me, אין שפחה אחר אישה. ein
shifchah achar isha.
So the father cannot resell her if the first master married her
and then now she is single again. Okay, so that is the
way, that is what Rabbi Akiva says. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer
omer, כיון שבגד בה. keivan shebagad bah. No, no, no, it is
not about her being married. It is once the father betrayed her
by selling her in the first place, שוב אינו רשאי למכרה, shuv
eino rashai lemochrah, he can never sell her again, which is אין
שפחה אחר שפחה, ein shifchah achar shifchah, even if she was not
married by the master. Once he sold her once, and now he
cannot sell her again. So do you read the word בגד beged
as cloak or as בגידה begidah as betrayal, as betrayal. Now
it is not exactly clear, I should say, which one is more
the way it is read versus the way it is written. So
רש״י Rashi has the גירסא, girsa, so the, well רש״י, Rashi, whatever,
there is a, by תוספות Tosafot and a רש״י Rashi figuring that
out. Let me just point out that תוספות Tosafot is bothered by
the fact that we would quote Rabbi Akiva before Rabbi Eliezer. Rabbi
Eliezer was Rabbi Akiva’s רבי. rebbi. So based on that and other
considerations, תוספות Tosafot puts Rabbi Eliezer first and Rabbi Akiva second. Anyway,
the גמרא Gemara somehow understands, and I am not going to try
to unpack it because it is not clear either way, that Rabbi
Eliezer in this debate is basing himself on how the פסוק pasuk
is written, not how it is read. So how can, how can
he say earlier that it is based on how it is read?
What, which one do you think yours is based more on how
it is written? How?
They both read and written the same way, aren't they?
So, so that is the point. Where is there a difference at
all? So רש״י Rashi says, well, the way it
is read makes it sound more like בגד beged because it would
read בבגדו בה bevigdo vah if it were בבגדו בה, bevigdo vah,
but anyway, it is not clear which way fits more with the
way it is read and the way it is written. Right, but
anyway, the גמרא Gemara assumes that the Rabbi Eliezer here, and it
is a question which position Rabbi Eliezer is taking, is based on
how it is written. So how could that fit with what you
claimed that Rabbi Eliezer goes by תרומותי, terumotai, which is how it
is read? So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא הכא בהא קמיפלגי. ela
hacha beha kamiflegi. Fine, forget the פסוק. pasuk. Here is what they
debate in the תרומה terumah case. רבי יהושע סבר, Rabbi Yehoshua savar,
הראויה לך שמור ושאינה ראויה לך לא תשמור. hara’uyah lecha shemor veshe’einah
ra’uyah lecha lo tishmor. It
is still based on the פסוק, pasuk, if you would, of נתתי
לך את משמרת תרומותי. natati lecha et mishmeret terumotai.
So רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says if it is לך, lecha, if
you are be able to benefit from it, then you have to
guard it. But once it is doubtfully, it is possibly טמא tamei
and you are stuck between and you cannot benefit from it, then
you have no responsibility to guard it. So focusing on the לך.
lecha. So once you have no responsibility to guard it, expose it,
and if it becomes טמא, tamei, then you can at least use
it as air freshener. That is what רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says.
And therefore, so and therefore, Rabbi Eliezer says no, either way you
have to protect it, and therefore even though it is doubtfully טמא.
tamei. you have to protect it. So the גמרא Gemara says ורבי
אליעזר הנמי חזיא היא. V'Rabbi Eliezer hanami chazeiyah hi. Why? He'll say
you know what, this also is considered fit for you. How's it
fit? I can't do anything with it. שמא יבוא אליהו ויטהרנו, Shema
yavo Eliyahu v'yitaharenu, it might be fit, you don't have all the
facts. So therefore, just because you have some, you are ignorant, does
not mean that objectively this תרומה truma is not fit for you.
Okay, your ignorance does not change the status of this תרומה. truma.
This תרומה truma might be טהור, tahor, so you have to protect
it. Okay, so that is what they debate about the תרומה truma
case, but going back to our case by the בכור, bechor, right
now we're saying that it's because it already has a מום, mum,
and the question is whether it is prohibited to make another מום,
mum, and as I tried to frame it, it is a question
whether the problem is about the act or about the end result,
which also ties into the question about גרמא grama and indirect. Now
let's take a look how the גמרא Gemara wraps this up. אמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי שמעון. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel
halacha k'Rabbi Shimon. We rule like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Now רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon in the משנה Mishna said you can actually do
it in a place where it makes a מום. mum. רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon in the ברייתא Braitah went even further and said you
can do it if it makes a מום mum and you can
even שחט shacht on the basis of that מום. mum. So that's
what the גמרא Gemara wants to know. משקיף לה רב נחמן בר
יצחק. Maskif la Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak. So רב נחמן בר יצחק
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak asks him, הי רבי שמעון, Hai Rabbi Shimon,
which רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? It's funny he uses the phrase משקיף
לה, maskif la, because משקיף לה maskif la is normally when you
have some text that creates like some type of a contradiction. Here
it was really just a question about clarification, right? He was really
asking for clarification. Which רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon are you ruling like?
אילימא רבי שמעון דמתניתין, Ilima Rabbi Shimon d'matnitin, if it's רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon of the משנה, Mishna, השתא לא אשמעינן שמואל דבר שאינו
מתכוין מותר? hashtah lo ashmeinan Shmuel davar she'eino mitkavein mutar? So why
this telling us that the הלכה halacha was like רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon was in the name of שמואל? Shmuel? But we already know
שמואל Shmuel rules that something that you're doing unintentionally is permissible. והא
רבי חייא בר אשי אמר רב הלכה כרבי יהודה. V'ha Rabbi Chiya
bar Ashi amar Rav halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda. רבי חייא בר אשי Rabbi
Chiya bar Ashi says in the name of רב Rav we rule
like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says אינו מתכוין, eino mitkavein, unintentional
acts, if something that might lead to an unintentional violation is prohibited.
ורב חנן בר אשי אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי שמעון. V'Rav Chanan bar
Ashi amar Shmuel halacha k'Rabbi Shimon. And רב חנן בר אשי Rav
Chanan bar Ashi says in the name of שמואל Shmuel that we
rule like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that אינו מתכוין eino mitkavein is
permissible. ורבי חייא בר אבין מתני לה בלא גברי. V'Rabbi Chiya bar
Avin matni lah belo gavrei. And רבי חייא בר אבין Rabbi Chiya
bar Avin teaches it without, you know, without like a whole line
of tradition. רב אמר הלכה כרבי יהודה. Rav amar halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda.
רב Rav says we rule like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, אינו מתכוין
eino mitkavein is forbidden. ושמואל אמר הלכה כרבי שמעון. U'Shmuel amar halacha
k'Rabbi Shimon. And שמואל Shmuel says we rule like רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. So to tell me we rule like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
like in the משנה, Mishna, who doesn't say you're allowed to שחט
shacht on it, he just says you're allowed to do it, why
do you need to tell me that שמואל Shmuel says this? We
know that he rules like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that דבר שאינו
מתכוין davar she'eino mitkavein is מותר. mutar. Now everybody should be jumping
up at me and saying what does it have to do with
אינו מתכוין? eino mitkavein? Until now we've been talking that it's that
you can do it even if you're definitely going to make a
blemish, right? And you can do it because it's making a מום
mum after a מום, mum, right? Which is how we explained it
before. It has nothing to do with אינו מתכוין. eino mitkavein. You're
definitely making a blemish. So there are two ways to answer this.
One is you're right, it's a reframing of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
Now still you would say okay fine, so it's not based on
blemish after blemish, it's based on אינו מתכוין. eino mitkavein. What do
you mean אינו מתכוין? eino mitkavein? You're definitely making a מום. mum.
You just don't care about that, you're trying to let the blood.
But that is normally by שבת Shabbat what we would call not
אינו מתכוין, eino mitkavein, we would normally call that מלאכה שאינה צריכה
לגופה. melacha she'eina tzricha l'gufah. You know what you're doing, but your
interest in it is different than what the prohibited nature of the
act is. You're doing it as a surgery, not as making of
מום. mum. But your intention is different, but that's not a normal
אינו מתכוין. eino mitkavein. Now you might remember that an earlier רש"י
Rashi actually claimed that that was an אינו מתכוין eino mitkavein as
well. Right, we had a גמרא Gemara and תוספות Tosafot points this
out. As I was reading this גמרא, Gemara, you know, I said
oh that's just like the earlier רש"י, Rashi, and then I realized
oh תוספות Tosafot already made the connection. So רש"י Rashi before the
גמרא Gemara talked about cutting hairs off of like a פרה אדומה
parah adumah and doing these types of things, and are you doing
it right, or remember you're trying to move the hair away to
check for a מום, mum, and are you therefore shearing an animal
that's קדשים kodashim or a בכור? bechor? And רש"י Rashi said that
even if you definitely are pulling the hairs out, since that's not
your purpose, it's called an אינו מתכוין. eino mitkavein. What a fascinating
idea that we take what normally is seemed to be an only
שבת Shabbat idea of מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha she'eina tzricha l'gufah
and apply it elsewhere and say no, maybe elsewhere as well, even
if you know the act you're doing, if you're doing it for
a completely different reason, maybe it's not defined as the same act
and it's linked to אינו מתכוין. eino mitkavein. So that would be
one way of reading this. And therefore yes, there's two ways of
understanding why רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon in the משנה Mishna allows it.
Either because it's a blemish after a blemish, or forget the blemish
after blemish, it's because your intent is to let blood and not
make a blemish. That's one minute, that's one way of reading it.
But the normal אינו מתכוין eino mitkavein is not that. The normal
אינו מתכוין eino mitkavein is is that you don't know that B
will result. You're always trying to do A. B might result, it
might not, but you don't care about it either way. And therefore
if it accidentally does result, it's not what you intended, it's not
your fault. That's, so how would you read that in the משנה?
Mishna? So this is what תוספות Tosafot says. תוספות Tosafot says it's
the difference between רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon in the משנה Mishna and
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon in the ברייתא. Braitah. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
in the משנה, Mishna, this is a very nice close reading. says
אף על פי שהוא עושה בו מום af al pi shehu oseh
bo mum and whereas רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon in the ברייתא Baraisa
says במקום
שעושה בו מום. bimkom sheoseh bo mum. So the way תוספות Tosfos
maybe or you know tries to argue is if you say במקום
שעושה בו מום bimkom sheoseh bo mum do it in a place
where a blemish will be made it sounds like a blemish is
definitely going to be made. And nevertheless you're allowed to do it.
So that ברייתא Baraisa where it says a place where a blemish
is made the only way to explain why רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
allowed it was because it was already it's allowed because it already
had a blemish. It's a blemish after blemish it definitely would be
made. But he says that's not the case of the משנה. Mishnah.
The case of the משנה Mishnah is you might maybe you will
make a blemish maybe you won't. So when רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says אף עושה בו מום af oseh bo mum he means even
if you might accidentally make a blemish. So according to תוספות Tosfos
that's what's going on that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon in the ברייתא
Baraisa had to be explained if it was allowed it was a
blemish after blemish that scenario was you were definitely making a blemish.
Whereas רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon in the משנה Mishnah could be read
like you're allowed to do it in a place where a blemish
might result. And therefore it's being explained as your classic אינו מתכוין.
aino miskavein. Okay?
So and it's accidental that the blemishes might
and
then it would be incidental not coincidental. Incidental yes.
So let's just finish this. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
If you're telling me that we rule like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
in the משנה Mishnah that you're allowed to do it then I
don't need שמואל Shmuel to tell it to me now. שמואל Shmuel
already told me אינו מתכוין aino miskavein is מותר mutar which either
means like רש"י Rashi you're definitely making a blemish but your intent
is otherwise and that redefines it which is a like a surprising
extension of אינו מתכוין. aino miskavein. Or like תוספות Tosfos the case
in the משנה Mishnah is one where you wouldn't have necessarily made
a blemish. And therefore of course you're allowed to do it according
to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. You're not intending for it. אלא רבי
שמעון דברייתא Ella Rabbi Shimon de-Baraisa it must be רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon of the ברייתא Baraisa who says who says not only are
you allowed to do it and not only if you definitely make
a blemish but he also says you're allowed to שחט shecht on
the basis of that מום. mum. And we're not concerned about a
policy consideration that if we let you שחט shecht you'll come to
do it even when you don't need to. Says the גמרא Gemara
and the גמרא Gemara says רבי אידי Rabbi Idi where is it
ורב ששת בריה דרבי אידי מתני לה בהדיא ve-Rav Sheshes berei de-Rabbi
Idi masni la be-hedya and רב ששת Rav Sheshes son of רבי
אידי Rabbi Idi teaches it explicitly אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל הלכה
כרבי שמעון דברייתא. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel halacha ke-Rabbi Shimon de-Baraisa.
We rule like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon of the ברייתא. Baraisa. You're
allowed to do it even if you definitely make a blemish and
once you do that you're even allowed to שחט shecht on the
basis of it. What is the reason? As I said one of
two reasons. Either it's like a blemish after a blemish which is
what the גמרא Gemara said before or the way the גמרא Gemara
is framing it now it's אינו מתכוין. aino miskavein. אינו מתכוין aino
miskavein either because it didn't necessarily result or a more drastic אינו
מתכוין aino miskavein since it wasn't why you were doing it it's
not defined as the act itself. Yes Charlie?
In מסכת שבת Masechet Shabbos there are debates over and over between
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon over אינו מתכוין.
aino miskavein. Yeah and but and this but this seems like that's
the
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that you can't do something if it's
certain to result in a prohibited action there which would seem to
be
no everybody agrees if it's certain yeah that's
what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon agrees that you can't that's what that
you can't correct.
But what
this seems like it would extend that more because it might even
he might you're this saying that it might even you're saying how
could
I your question is how could רש"י Rashi say אינו מתכוין aino
miskavein means you're intending something different and that's permitted according to רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon if רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon does not allow אינו
מתכוין aino miskavein to be פסיק רישא. pesik reisheh. Yes that's what
so the רמב"ם Rambam already has that פסק. psak. Because the רמב"ם
Rambam already says by שבת Shabbos the רמב"ם Rambam already says אינו
מתכוין aino miskavein פסיק רישא pesik reisheh is אסור asur right for
רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? But
oh he has the reverse? One minute. But he has no he
has מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha she'eina tzericha legufa let me remember
he has it split in one of those ways. He has מלאכה
שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha she'eina tzericha legufa is חייב chayav
okay I have to remind myself. Anyway but it is possible to
distinguish between these two cases. It's possible to say that if you
know exactly what you're doing and you're redefining it which is מלאכה
שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha she'eina tzericha legufa what I'm doing here is
surgery. I am not doing making a מום mum right then that
actually defines this as surgery. You're owning what you're doing and you're
defining it in a particular way. If you're trying to do something
else and accidentally make a מום mum then you haven't redefined what
you've done. And since it was going to result we don't call
that surgery we call that making a מום. mum. So it actually
is possible to be more lenient by מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha
she'eina tzericha legufa than it would by an אינו מתכוין aino miskavein
פסיק רישא. pesik reisheh. Okay? But you're right that exactly is what
you would have to say according to רש"י Rashi and that's similar
to a פסק psak of the רמב"ם Rambam but I have to
remind myself exactly the רמב"ם's Rambam פסק. psak.
Yes? I'm sure everybody's crazy but I'm still on the father selling
the daughter. It's just driving me insane. And there are a number
of things here that I'm going to raise and I know it's
I'm sorry it's slowing us down. One does a father ever sell
a son? No.
Okay we won't even talk about that. The second question is there
was a there was a substatement here that said it was like
in paren that he can't do this again if she's a minor
implying that if she's not a minor he can then
no if she's not a minor she can't he couldn't do it
in the first place.
He couldn't do it in the first oh. He couldn't do it
in the first place. Right. I guess I misunderstood that.
No, no. So, yeah. It's only if she's a minor does this
whole conversation apply.
But if she marries and then becomes widowed, he can then- That's
the question.
She marries and becomes widowed, can he do it again if she's
still a minor? And that's what we're saying, and that's what we're
saying is no, that the תורה Torah is prohibiting that, but under
what circumstances? If only in the circumstances of after she became married,
or even in the circumstances of even if she wasn't married and
just was taken as a slave and then- How
does all this get allowed? How do we Jews allow such- I
mean, there was רחל, Rachel, there was לאה. Leah. How do we
live with ourselves and just move on to the cow, the horse,
the sheep, the deer? And there's a woman being sold by her
father. I got it.
So, okay. So first of all- Jewish woman! Yes. This is not
just the גמרא, Gemara, this is פסוקים pesukim in the תורה, Torah,
and this is discussed in מסכת קידושין Masechet Kiddushin at greater length,
which we can have time- more time to discuss it. But the
short answer is, the short answer is, is that these- is that
there were actual- there's two parts to this short answer. Number one
is there were actual societal realities which made that this was necessary.
And the- you know,
because women would not be able to provide for themselves, fathers had
to make sure that daughters would be provided for, and that this
was one way of essentially ensuring that their daughters would ultimately have
somebody to provide for them. The proof that there was a societal
need for it is that the גמרא Gemara even instituted when there
was not a father to give the mother and brothers the right
to do this, and they were not doing it just because they
wanted to be mean to the girl, but there was real sort
of economic societal need for these types of institutions. That's part of
the answer. The other part of the answer is, is that what
the תורה Torah is actually doing, like it does in the case
of slavery, is that the תורה Torah is actually coming and taking
an institution which we were not- the society was not yet ready
to get rid of and trying to make it more moral and
put it on a path with this, you know, the necessary path
that it has to be in order to- you know, to move
out of that- of that situation. So that is the second part
of that answer. Okay? So it's basically- the way you can think
about it, how the תורה Torah allows slavery. תורה Torah came with
slavery? No. It's trying to correct that institution. And that's what I
believe is happening here as well. Okay? But that- I see you're
not happy, but we will leave it for more when we do
קידושין. Kiddushin. Yes.
It's kind of hard to follow up with that train of thought.
I'm going to go back to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. You don't
usually use רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, do we? I mean, this is
one of the few times, you know- Okay, fine, but
that's- I mean, but-
although the רמב"ם Rambam doesn't, and the רמב"ם Rambam splits his vote
there, which
is what I was referring to. Were there general rules, like how
does it go? Something מחבירו ולא מחבירו, mechaveiro velo mechaveiro, is that
רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon?
Yes, but anyway, okay, fine. There are always exceptions. Rules are made
for exceptions, for every exception. Okay,
let's keep on going. Okay, next משנה. Mishnah. הצורם אוזן בבכור הרי
זה לא ישחוט עולמית. Hatzorem ozen bevachor, harei zeh lo yishchot olamit.
If somebody- now, before we were talking about that you had to-
because it was blood clotting and policy-wise should we let you שחט
shecht after you've made a מום mum or not, but there we
might have even allowed you to make the מום. mum. Here you're
intentionally doing it. You're making a nick in the ear. This is
often an example- a classic example of a מום mum as you
remember from the dog and the קרפלך kreplach there was a nick
in the ear because those don't heal. Apparently other parts of the
body it heals better, the ear- a cut in the ear won't
heal. So you went ahead and you did this. You are never
allowed to שחט shecht on the basis of it. Here רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, וחכמים אומרים, vechachamim omrim, never שחט shecht not only on
the basis of it, you can never שחט shecht this בכור. bechor.
You have to treat it like it always has a מום mum
for the rest of its- it always doesn't have a מום mum
for the rest of its life. וחכמים אומרים, vechachamim omrim, the Sages
say, נולד בו מום אחר ישחוט עליו. nolad bo mum acher yishchot
alav. No, if there's another blemish you can. So here's the point.
Do we basically say you can't benefit from this act itself? So
that's what everybody agrees, that's what the חכמים Chachamim say. But then
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer takes it one step further and basically says
if all you say is I can't benefit from this act itself,
there's no disincentive, right? It's like when the תורה Torah says what
do you do if you steal something, if it's גזילה וגניבה, gezeilah
vekenaveh, give it back. Well, you know, that's not- that's not so
much of a dis- oh, if you make a blemish you won't
be able to benefit from it. So I'll make a blemish, maybe
they won't find out that I made it, and then I'll benefit.
Even if they find out I made it, okay, nothing ventured, nothing
lost, you know. So therefore רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says no, if
you made a blemish you'll never be able to שחט shecht this
בכור bechor even if there's another blemish. So here's a question about
how far do we go to try to create a disincentive to
prevent you from doing it. Yes, very smart.
So according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer you're supposed to probably kill
it, right?
Because then you have a- you're not allowed to kill it, so
you have to just-
let me sort of put it in a place
where it's more likely to die, right?
Yeah, not
exactly clear if you'd be allowed to do that. I know, I
understand, but on the other hand it's- it's קדשים תמימים kodshim temimim
that you're not allowed to destroy. So you have to- you've got-
you've got a בכור bechor now that you've got- you've got to
support for the rest of its life. That was a pretty serious
disincentive. So let's take a look. ומי קניס רבי אליעזר עולם? Umi
kanis Rabbi Eliezer olam? Does רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer really make these
type of like forever fines? ורמינהי, Varaminhi, I'll ask you, מי שהיה
לו בהרת ונקצצה. mi shehayah lo baheret veniktetzah. You had a spot
of leprosy on you and it accidentally got cut off. Okay, טהור,
tahor, you're טהור tahor because you no longer have it on you.
Okay, certainly- the כהן kohen hasn't seen it yet. Now perhaps even
if he has seen it, but now it's no longer there, right?
One of the ways you're טהור tahor from your leprosy, when it's
no longer there. Well, it's no longer there because you cut it
off. Okay, fine. That doesn't happen by itself. קצצו במתכוין, Kitzetzo b'mitkaven,
you intentionally cut it off. All right, now we can't let you
benefit from that. רבי אליעזר אומר לכשיולד לו נגע אחר יטהר
הימנו. Rebbe Eliezer omer l'chsheyivaled lo nega acher yitaher mimenu. Here's how
you'll become טהור. tahor. We cannot, we cannot ever let, we have
to treat it as if this blemish is still there. Okay, but
if you get another blemish of leprosy and become טהור tahor from
that, then we can say the same way you became טהור tahor
from the second blemish, you would have become טהור tahor from the
first one and then you could become טהור. tahor.
Could it be like a שחין shechin in the same place?
Not even the same place. But you might wait your whole life,
whatever you got, you got another blemish and then you became טהור.
tahor. We'll, we'll allow ourselves to assume that that's an indication that
if, that this process of it clearing up would have cleared up
the first one as well. But you could wait your whole life
for that to happen. Okay, but that's what רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer
says. וחכמים אומרים, V'chachamim omrim, the חכמים Chachamim are even more strict.
עד שתפרח בכולו, Ad shetifrach b'kulo, the only way you're going to
be טהור tahor is if right now you have leprosy on your
entire body. Because then, right, one way you're טהור tahor is if
it covers your whole body. If it covers your whole body, then
you could say, so even if it's still been here, right, fine,
it would have covered your whole body and you would have been
טהור. tahor. Either that, או עד שתמעט פהרתו, o ad shetim'et paharato,
or until it shrinks. Now what does it mean shrinks? So רש״י
Rashi says it means it shrinks before you cut it off, which
then is like almost like a no-brainer, then it wasn't even a
problem. תוספות Tosafot says what it means is, is that let's say
the whole thing was a certain size, a גריס gris is the
size of it, you cut off half, like half of it, and
then the remaining half totally disappeared. So even had the part that
you cut off still been there, it would not have been the
requisite size. But basically what the חכמים Chachamim are saying is, we
can only make it טהור tahor is if not only it, is
if even had it been there right now, still there right, we're
going to consider it like it's still there.
And, and what? One
minute.
And it was going to consider it like it's still there. And
the only way you'll be טהור tahor is if you would be
טהור tahor even with it still being there. Now, what's the issue?
רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer does not say that you're stuck for life.
He at least gives you one out. You can get leprosy again
and become טהור. tahor. In our case, by the, by the שחי
shechi who says you're stuck for life. It's like this, wait, what's
this? All right, so we're going to see a couple of possible
answers. רבה בר רב יוסף רמי תבייהו. Rabbah bar Rav Yosef rami
tavaihu. So רבה בר רב יוסף Rabbah bar Rav Yosef gives the
following answer. כי קניס רבי אליעזר בממונו בגופו לא קניס. Ki kanis
Rebbe Eliezer b'mamono, b'gufo lo kanis. When does רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer
say you're going to be stuck for life? If it's your property.
So you have a sheep for the rest of your life that
you can't שחט. shecht. When it's your person, so you're going to
become a מצורע metzora for the rest of your life, that's a
little too drastic. ממונו Mamono and, so number one is how drastic
it is. And number two is also the following. ממונו איכא למימר
דאתי למיעבד. Mamono, ika l'meimar d'ati l'meiavad. Number one, the way רש״י
Rashi explains this is, if we don't fine you, then you'll come
to make a מום mum in your, in your sheep. Nothing ventured,
nothing off. Okay, גופו מי איכא למימר דאתי למיעבד. gufo, mi ika
l'meimar d'ati l'meiavad. By your body, who's going to say that it
will ever happen? Now the question is דאתי למיעבד, d'ati l'meiavad, you'll
come to do it or it will ever happen. The way רש״י
Rashi reads it regardless is, that you will never
want to make a,
cut a, even if we limit ourselves to saying, okay, you're going
to be טמא tamei until it gets another, another צרעת tzara'at and
it heals, right, you don't know if that'll ever happen. And since
you don't know if that'll ever happen, right,
that's a big enough disincentive that we can allow that to be
your one out. Okay, so therefore yes, here we don't have to
do it forever. Number one is it's about your person, so we
don't have to be so mean, and number two, not mean is
the wrong word, so strict. And number two is, is that it's
a pretty big disincentive regardless. אמר רבא דרבי אליעזר דרבי אליעזר קשיא
דרבנן דרבנן לא קשיא? Amar Rava, d'Rebbe Eliezer d'Rebbe Eliezer kashya, d'Rabbanan
d'Rabbanan lo kashya? So רבא Rava says what? Your body דרבי אליעזר
d'Rebbe Eliezer contradicts himself. You're not bothered דרבנן d'Rabbanan contradict themselves? They
go from one extreme to the next. In our משנה Mishnah they
say that, you know, the blemish, another blemish is okay. And here
they say you're stuck for life. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
אלא דרבי אליעזר דרבי אליעזר לא קשיא כדישנינן. ela d'Rebbe Eliezer d'Rebbe
Eliezer lo kashya k'dishaninan. רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer is not a problem
like you said. He's more lenient in the case of צרעת tzara'at
because it's about your person and because there's a huge disincentive anyway.
רבנן דרבנן נמי לא קשיא. Rabbanan d'Rabbanan nami lo kashya. The רבנן
Rabbanan also aren't a contradiction. Why? הכא במאי דעביד קנסוה הכא במאי
דעביד קנסוה. Hacha b'mai d'avid kinsu, hacha b'mai d'avid kinsu. That it's
not about as much about policy as about like a formal approach.
What you did wrong, that is what we are going to counteract.
What does this mean? במאי חזי למישרי בהאי מומא. B'mai chazei l'misharei
b'hai muma. In our משנה, Mishnah, what did you try to do?
To make this animal permissible by making a מום. mum. בהאי מומא
קנסו רבנן. B'hai muma kinsu Rabbanan. It's like the מום mum was
never made. And therefore fine, if the מום mum was never made,
if it gets another מום, mum, you're okay. So all we did
is we essentially counteracted your action. We treated it as if there
was no
מום. mum. בהאי מומא לא לישרי ליה. B'hai muma lo lisharei lei.
This מום mum will never be a basis of making him permissible.
It's like there's no מום. mum. והכא במאי דעביד קנסוה. V'hacha b'mai
d'avid kinsu. Here we focus on what you did. What and we
fined you. What did you do? דקא בעי למיטהר נפשיה בהאי קציצה.
Deka baei lemithar nafshieh behai katzitza. You tried to make yourself טהור
tahor by cutting away this spot of leprosy. So בהאי קציצה קנסוהו
רבנן. Behai katzitza kenasuhu rabbanan. So we made it like you didn't
cut away this spot of leprosy. So what does that mean if
you didn't cut away this spot of leprosy? Like it's still here.
Which means even if you get another leprosy and get purified from
it, we're going to view it's irrelevant. This spot is always going
to still be here. And therefore, that's what you're stuck with. So
it's basically one of them is much more sort of societal policy,
like and which is רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, what do we need
to keep people in line? The concept of fine also makes sense
because we're really like trying to just focus on correcting behavior or
preventing behavior. And the rabbis are much more formalists. You did something
wrong, we negate your action. It's like your action didn't take place.
Whether that means that there's no disincentive like our משנה, Mishna, or
whether that means that there's a profound disincentive like the case of
צרעת, Tzaraat, that's not our issue. Our issue is we have to
negate your action as if it did not happen. And we continue
here.